Okay, so in this video
then, we are going to
discuss some additional
common procurement tools.
So one very common
tool that is asked about on
the exam is this one
called a biddis conference.
Now, not every industry uses biddis
conferences, but it is used heavily in
government contracting, and there are
other industries that use it.
Now, a biddis conference is basically a
meeting with all of the potential sellers,
at all of the potential vendors,
they're in the same meeting.
It could be a face-to-face meeting or it
could be a conference call, or a Zoom
meeting, but it is a meeting with all of
the potential sellers in the same meeting.
And the whole idea is to make sure there's
a clear and common understanding of the
procurement process, clear and common
understanding of what the project is about.
Now, the whole principle behind this or
one of the principles behind this is to
try and prevent any kind of favoritism
towards one particular vendor on trying to
prevent any kind of collusion between the
buyer and the seller organization.
It's supposed to be a level playing field.
Everyone has access to the same
information.
So typically what happens then is the
buyer, say a government agency,
will send an RFP, a
request for a proposal to the
seller, inviting them to
the business conference.
now they have a certain time period in
which the vendor can ask questions right
so they'll reach out to several sellers
and then they have a certain deadline
where they need to submit all of their
questions by and all of those questions
will be answered by the buyer and those
questions will be available to everybody
right not just the vendors
ask those questions
but they will be available to everyone.
So again, it's supposed to be a level
playing field.
So the bidders conference said,
all of the vendors then, they basically
come to this bidders conference,
and it's an open dialogue.
They all have the same information.
So no vendor can, like I said,
no vendor can claim that another vendor
had preferential treatment is to try and
prevent all of that.
So in the actual bidders conference
itself, it's an open dialogue.
So the vendor is asking
questions in front of
all of their, you know,
all of their competitors.
And the buyer is answering questions.
The buyer is asking questions.
And the potential vendors are answering
questions.
Right.
So again, it's an open dialogue.
Now, there are some different variations
of bidders conferences.
Some of you may have gone
to bidders conferences where
none of the potential
vendors are allowed to speak.
I mean, sure, there is.
There's different variations.
But for the purpose of
the PMP exam, assume
that the bidders conference
is an open dialogue.
Now, most vendors actually dislike going
to a biddis conference.
Most vendors don't like going to them.
And why?
Because they've got all their competitors
in the same meeting.
If it's a face-to-face meeting,
all the competitors are right there.
Or even in conference call.
All the competitors are there.
So they have to be careful about what
they're going to say.
you want to try and show
a competitive advantage,
but you don't want to
let out any trade secrets.
And then plus, when you're asking
questions, you don't want to show that
there's any weaknesses in your
organization.
So all the attendees are very careful
about what they're actually saying and
what they're actually discussing in a
bidder's conference.
But either way, though, a bidder's
conference is a, it's supposed to be a
meeting then with all of the potential,
vendors, all of the potential sellers,
and an open dialogue.
Now, there may be several rounds of
bidders conferences.
First round might be just more of a
screening session, then they may have
another round of bidders conferences,
right?
Or there might just be one bidders
conference altogether.
And there's different
names, different organizations
have different names for a
bidder's conference as well.
So generally then, you
have a biddis conference
before the submission of
any bids, naturally, right?
Because what they're doing is the vendors
are trying to understand what the project
is about, they're supposed to come to,
or the vendors are supposed to have a
clear and common understanding so that
then they can supply an accurate bid.
And then after they've supplied these
bids, these proposals, then the buyer is
going to review those proposals,
right?
They're going to evaluate those proposals
and then select one of those vendors.
Now, a couple of other,
Other common procurement
tools, advertising and
marketing, naturally, right?
So we've decided to outsource the work,
well, how a vendor is going to come to us?
Well, let's advertise the opportunity,
right?
Or we do our own market research,
before we reach out to particular vendors,
right?
Let's say we don't want to reach out to
vendors, we want
vendors to reach out to us.
So we would advertise that opportunity.
also a proposal evaluation vendors are
going to give you their bids they're going
to give you their proposals so whether
it's after a bidders conference or you
don't have a bidist conference you've
reached out to a vendor they're going to
give you their bid they're going to give
you their proposal and so you're going to
evaluate those proposals which of these
proposals is going to work for us which
are the best one the best proposal and so
then we would reach out to this vendor or
rather we would select this vendor and
then negotiate a contract with them.
And there's many, many different ways of
evaluating the proposal from your vendor.
It may have something
called a simple screening
system where they have to
meet this minimum criteria.
So as a very simple example, project
managers have to be P&P certified.
That's the screening system.
So of all these vendors that have given us
a proposal, If these project managers are
not P&P certified, those are the ones we
will eliminate first.
That's our minimum criteria.
Or we may have something called a
weighting system or a scoring model.
Based on certain criteria, we will give
them an arbitrary score.
And then we would add up all of those
scores and then we can see which is the
highest ranking proposal, lowest ranking
proposal.
That can help us prioritize some of these
vendors.
or it could just be based on some kind of
seller's rating system, based on their
past performance or some review,
online reviews, based on their online
ratings, based on how they're rated on,
say, the Better Business Bureau,
right, and other types of rating systems
as well.
So that's another way of evaluating
proposals.
And there's many, many ways as well.
These are just a couple of ways that I've
just mentioned, right?
So these are just a couple of
examples, but there are many,
many ways that you would
evaluate a seller's proposal.
And again, you're doing some work in your
house.
You've reached out to a few contractors.
You've got these proposals.
Well, you're going to determine which of
these is going to work for us.
And so the source selection criteria that
we discussed in a prior video,
that would be very relevant here as well.
They have to meet this source selection.
They have to meet this minimum criteria.
For example, lowest cost vendor.
We're just going to go with the lowest
cost vendor.
So that could be our proposal evaluation.
So these are just some of the additional
common procurement tools.